Finding Aid for the Charles K. Adams Santa Fe Railroad Collection LSC.0343
UCLA Library Special Collections
Charles K. Adams Santa Fe Railroad collection
1850-1951
UCLA Library Special Collections
Adams, Charles K.
LSC.0343
3.0 Linear Feet (6 boxes and 1 oversize package)
In 1868, Cyrus K. Holliday obtained a charter and raised capital for a new railroad that began running in Kansas the following year. He dreamed of a railway to replace covered wagons along the Santa Fe Trail between Independence, Missouri and Santa Fe, New Mexico. By 1890, 9000 miles of track had been laid. The railway became bankrupt in the Panic of 1893, but was bought by Edward Payson Ripley, who added 2000 miles of track creating one of the largest privately-owned rail systems in the world. The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, clippings, maps, books, and other printed material relating to the formation, development, and history of the Santa Fe Railroad.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles K. Adams, 1953.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942302953606533
Biography
In 1868 farmer, lawyer and first mayor of Topeka, Kansas, Cyrus K. Holliday obtained a charter and raised capital for a new railroad that began running in Kansas the following year; he dreamed of a railway to replace covered wagons along the Santa Fe Trail between Independence, Missouri and Santa Fe, New Mexico; by 1890, 9000 miles of track had been laid; the railway became bankrupt in the Panic of 1893, but was bought by Edward Payson Ripley, who added 2000 miles of track; it became one of the largest privately-owned rail systems in the world, with passenger service from Chicago to San Francisco and Los Angeles, and with the bulk of its business in freight.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, clippings, maps, books, and other printed material relating to the formation, development, and history of the Santa Fe Railroad.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence and historical material (Box 1).
Official papers, Adams's notebooks, newspaper clippings, photographs (Box 2).
Rules and regulations of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway System (Box 3).
Ephemera and pamphlets published by and about the Santa Fe Railroad Co. (Box 4).
Books (Box 5).
Newspapers and clippings (Box 6).
Adams's large notebook (Box 7).
Items Removed from Collection
5 maps (3 maps on Belgian railroad routes, 2 maps on French railroad routes.
1 newspaper clipping from Los Angeles Times, December 4, 1945.
Railroads -- West (U.S.) -- History.; Adams, Charles K.--Archives.; Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Company; Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Company--History--Sources.
- Correspondence and Historical Material
  - Correspondences and notes, December 4, 1931-April 9, 1945.; (23 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence typescripts, holograph, January 21, 1939-January 1951. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes letters from and to Phil Townsend Hanna, Editor, Westways.
  - The Santa Fe Railway, by De Witt O'Kieffe, n.d.; (21 pieces, Typescript) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Century Annals of San Bernardino County,, by L.A. Ingersoll., 1769-1904; (13 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Early Railroad Efforts, including the Texas & Pacific. Excerpt from History of San Diego 1542-1908, by William E. Smythe, 1850-1877. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Record of Board of Supervisor's Meeting held, January 9, 1868.; (4 pieces, photocopy and typescript) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tri-partite Agreement, January 31, 1880.; (14 pieces, blueprint copy) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History of the Santa Fe's entry into Los Angeles, 1880-1890.; (15 pieces, typescript and holograph) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brief history of California Southern Railroad Company as abstracted from San Diego Union Files, by Mrs. Joseph Weidel, January 1, 1882-November 28, 1885.; (21 pieces, typescript) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    With related correspondence.
  - Excerpts from the History of Pasadena, by Hiram A. Reid, 1882-1887.; (3 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Railroad celebrations, 1885.; (5 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - That Old Station Platform at Needles in 1886, by Charles Battye., (7 pieces, print) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    [Also], holograph letters from C. Battye to C.K. Adams.
  - Historical review of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway Company., (9 pieces, Blueprint copy) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - History and Directory of Riverside County, 1893-94.; (4 pieces, typescript) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Valley Road, 1896.; (67 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Yearly Reports to the President and Board of Directors of the San Francisco & San Joaquin Valley Railway Company, by W.B. Storey Jr., January 30, 1896-1899.; (38 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Article from the American Railway Bridges and Buildings, 1898.; (10 pieces, photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorandum from old file on San Pedro breakwater,, by C.K. Adams., 1898-1910; (5 pieces, transcript and holograph) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Historical review of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway Company, compiled by G. Holterhoff, Jr., (48 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    General note
    Partial duplication in Adams's notebook, Box 2.
  - History of Oakland and East Side Railroad Company, 1901-1927.; (8 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous material on the history of Santa Fe Railroad., (66 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Santa Fe and Los Angeles Harbor Railway Company, 1937.; (3 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous charts, relating to A.T.S.F. system, 1867-1941.; (Blueprints) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Schedules of employees time cards from Valley Division, Los Angeles Division and Albuquerque Division, prior, 1916.; (Typescripts) (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Official Papers, Adams's Notebooks, Newspaper Clippings, Photographs
  - Santa Fe Railroad from Los Angeles to Holbrook, Prepared by W.M. Balling, consulting mining engineer., March 8, 1943.; (11 pieces, typescript) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Santa Fe Railroad, Barstow to San Francisco, 1944.; (Typescript) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Line between Los Angeles and San Diego by C.K. Adams, November 24, 1944.; (Typescript) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Santa Fe News Bureau Newsletter, September 11, 1947.; (1 piece) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Southern California Education Tour,, by R.S. Hirsch., 1950; (Typescript and holograph) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Notes.
  - Correspondence on tank cars used in transporting helium gas, 1945.; (7 pieces, typescript and photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - C.K. Adams's notebooks. (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
    Including Historical review of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway Company, compiled by G. Holterhoff, Jr.
    Duplication in box 1, folder 19.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1886 and 1941.; (2 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs., (3 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Rules and Regulations of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway System
  - Through Train Service, October 1889.; (1 item) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Distance between stations on Santa Fe System, May 15, 1909. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Freight Tariff no.4, July 20, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rules Governing the Transportation Freight Traffic, August 1, 1897. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rules Governing the Transportation Freight Traffic, July 1, 1913. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rules Governing the Transportation Freight Traffic, October 15, 1927. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Freight Tariff and Classification Rules, October 1, 1928. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Supplement No.2.
  - Official Freight Shippers: Guide and Directory of Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe System, (1930). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Official Freight Shippers: Guide and Directory, (1934). (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Contract for Unified Operation of Railroad Facilities at Los Angeles, February 1, 1928. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Santa Fe Railroad, Albuquerque and Belen to Los Angeles, San Diego and Phoenix, March 1945. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Statement of Fred G. Gurley, president, Santa Fe System Lines before the Interstate Commerce Commission, November 28, 1949. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Pamphlets, Ephemera, Published by and about the Santa Fe Railroad Company
  - Publications of the Santa Fe Railroad Company
    - Hough, Waltes: The Moki Snake Dance ()., 1902 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Record-Breaking Run of the Scott Special over the Santa Fe, July 1905. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Santa Fe Employees' Magazine, June 1908. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      (Given by the Los Angeles Historical Society)
    - Titan of Chasms Grand Canyon of Arizona, (c.1910).; (3 copies) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Historical review of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway Company, 1914. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Grand Canyon Outings, March 1927. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Along Your Way., (2 issues) (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Railroad, 1941 and 1945.; (2 issues) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Santa Fe Today, May 1, 1945. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Santa Fe Magazine, 1923-1950.; (4 issues) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Publications about the Santa Fe Railroad
    - A review of Railway Operations,; American railroads, their growth and development; Quiz on railroads and railroading., 1947; (7 items) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Balduin Locomotives, October 1, 1939. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets, ephemera. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Books
  - The Grand Canyon of Arizona, 1906.; (2 items) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Higgins, C.A. New Guide to the Pacific Coast, Santa Fe Route, 1899-1914. (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    Includes 6 different editions of the book.
  - Carr, Clark E. History of Bringing The Atchison, Topeka & Santa Fe Railway to Galesburg, 1913. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Newspapers, Newspaper Clippings
  - Atchison Daily Globe, September 14, 1940; September 16, 1940. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - California Names-A Gazetteer, Chapters 1-43. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Progress Bulletin, January 13, 1941. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Topeka Daily Capitol, September 8, 1940. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1902-1949. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- C.K. Adams's notebook. (Box 7)